Guide to the Emirates Bird Records Committee records AD.MC.057
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Emirates Bird Records Committee records
1973-2019
bulk, 1989-2010
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Hellyer, Peter
Emirates Bird Records Committee
AD.MC.057
8.84 Linear Feet in 11 file boxes and 3 flat boxes.
28.6 Megabytes in 49 digital files
Documents, correspondence, reports, and bird-watching logs compiled by members of the Emirates Bird Records Committee (EBRC), from the 1980s to the early 2000s. The EBRC, a group of predominantly expatriate volunteers living in the United Arab Emirates, sought to document and verify sightings of various bird species throughout the Emirates.
Conditions governing access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Peter Hellyer in July 2019, with accretions in July and August 2020, and June 2023.
Arrangement
The EBRC Records are arranged into six series: I. Early records, II. Group Bird Record forms: by year, III. Group Bird Record forms: by individual, IV. Other records: analog, V. Other records, digital, VI. Oversize. Records are generally arranged in either alphabetical order (by folder title) or chronological order.
The records that comprise series II. and series III. were originally bundled together by year, with dividers identifying bird record forms kept by specific individuals. That distinctionn has been maintained, with series II. representing bird record forms, written reports by groups or individuals who visited the UAE, correspondence, and notes, including "phone-in" sightings of bird-species that were written down by Colin Richardson or Peter Hellyer. Series III. consists of bird record forms that were originally kept together under the names of the individuals who maintained these forms, and who typically lived in the UAE and kept such records over a longer period of time
Historical note
The Emirates Bird Records Committee (EBRC) was formed in the early 1990s by a group of British amateur ornithologists resident in the United Arab Emirates. In prior decades, efforts had been made to draw up a list of bird species that had been documented in the UAE, with one of the earliest lists being that compiled by a member of the British Army, on secondment to the Abu Dhabi Defence Force (ADDF), Lt. Col. J.D. Wellings, in 1973, with his survey of the birds of Abu Dhabi island.
In the following years, Mrs. F.E. Warr, of the Ornithological Society of the Middle East, compiled a more comprehensive list for the entire country, which by 1988 had listed several hundred bird species. This included historical data from the early 1970s, but from around 1980, drew primarily upon records collated by members of the Emirates Natural History Group, in Abu Dhabi, and the allied Dubai Natural History Group. In 1989, Colin Richardson, a British architect based in Dubai and Bird Recorder for the Dubai NHG, took over the maintenance of the list as well as the role of "UAE Bird Recorder," coordinating the receipt of information submitted by observers throughout the country. Shortly after assuming the role of UAE Bird Recorder, Richardson introduced a new standardized form that observers could use in the field to record the species that they observed. Designed in a matrix format, it listed all of the documented bird species in the left margin, with locations across the UAE listed across the top of each sheet.
By this time, an informal network of observers was active in locations ranging from Fujairah in the east to the westernmost reaches of Abu Dhabi emirate, while some made bird observations while working on offshore oil exploration sites in the Gulf. Many observers were resident expatriates who were members of the two natural history groups. Richardson also received bird-logs submitted by observers who visited from Europe or the United Kingdom during extended trips to the region. For several years, prior to his own departure from the Emirates, Richardson also ran commercial bird tours for overseas visitors.
Desiring a more systematic approach to collecting, assessing, and preserving such records of bird sightings, the EBRC was formed in 1993, holding its first meeting at the home of its first chair, Erik Hirschfeld, in Abu Dhabi. Four other members were chosen for the committee, including Richardson, and they met several times a year during the following years. One of the main tasks of the committee was to assess records submitted to them, in particular the records of sightings of rare species, usually defined as species that had been observed fewer than 20 times.
Periodically, members of the EBRC would publish updated lists of the birds of the UAE as well as newly documented rare species, often doing so in the publication Emirates Bird Records (EBR), compiled and edited by Richardson. Following the emergence of the internet, EBRC members began to circulate records of assessments by e-mail, rather than at meetings. A new Recorder, Tommy Pedersen, also established a website, http://www.uaebirding.com, in 2005, containing extensive data, including the results of EBRC assessments. From 2011, all data has been shared with the Cornell Lab of Ornithology in the United States, which maintains the eBird database (https://ebird.org/home), to which both scientists and the general public can upload data. UAE data uploaded to eBird is then assessed by the EBRC Recorder. Birdwatching as a pastime and the scientific study of UAE birdlife has expanded in recent years, attracting both native Emiratis and expatriates. This has helped to refute, once and for all, the assertion which, according to Col. Wellings, used to greet new arrivals, namely, that "there are no birds in Abu Dhabi!"
Content Description
The records of the Emirates Bird Records Committee (EBRC) contain a variety of reports, correspondence, notes, and documents related to bird-watching in the United Arab Emirates, but the predominant type of documentation are detailed bird-logs kept by volunteer observers and collected by members of the EBRC, chiefly Colin Richardson and Peter Hellyer, during the 1990s and early 2000s.
The series titled "Early Records" consists of a small number of items collected and created prior to 1989, the date when Colin Richardson assumed the role of UAE Bird Recorder. These include bird logs from a few of the most active observers, as well as earlier bird lists, including those compiled by Lt. Col. Wellings in 1973 and Mrs. F.E. Warr beginning in 1982, the latter of which became the foundation of the list maintained by Richardson and the EBRC.
The series "Group Bird Records Forms andn Reports-by year" and "Group Bird Records Forms--Individual" are the most extensive part of this collection, and contain detailed bird logs kept by observers and submitted to Richardson and other members of the EBRC. The logs were usually a standardized form, arranged as a matrix, with bird species printed on the left margin, and locations in the UAE printed along the top of the form. Observers often kept these for a period of time, submitting them on a monthly, quarterly, or annual basis. With granular data about sightings of individual species on specific dates and locations, this may be helpful in tracking changes in the population and extent of certain species in the region during the time period covered. Additional documents in these series include reports from observers visiting the region, correspondence to Richardson, and other notes and documents related to sightings of specific bird species in the country.
The series "Other records (analog)" contains documents related to projects carried out by EBRC members, such as the inventory of rare birds in the UAE, or reprints and other reference materials collected by the group. "Other records (digital)" contains minutes of meetings of the EBRC, beginning with the first meeting in 1993, as well as collected reports and publications in which the EBRC took part, including the last several issues of the "Emirates Bird Report" (ca. 1995-2000) and subsequent monthly and annual reports of the birds of the UAE (circa 2002-2010).
The last series, "Oversize," consists of computer printouts from Peter Hellyer, that comprise the inventories of birds in the UAE, compiled by data from observers, primarily from years prior to the establishment of the EBRC. These are typically alphabetic lists of bird species, followed by a chronological list of sightings of a given specie, along with the dates and observers recording that sighting. These could be useful for an overview of sightings for a specific bird specie, for the time period from the late 1970s to the late 1980s.
Preservica Internal URL
https://eu.preservica.com/explorer/explorer.html#prop:4&34b19b4b-904c-4960-80b7-127381d99d01
Preservica Public URL
https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|34b19b4b-904c-4960-80b7-127381d99d01/
Birds -- United Arab Emirates; Hellyer, Peter
- Early records, 1973-1988
  - The Birds of Abu Dhabi Island: a systematic list, compiled Lt. Col. J.D. Wellings, June 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A List of Birds of the United Arab Emirates, by Mrs. F.E. Warr, update of 1982 list, December 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antrobus, Peter, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cave, Andrew, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapman, J.A.B. (Adrian), 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miles, G.A., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reaney, Len, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Taylor, Ian, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous lists, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous list, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Group bird record forms: by year, 1989-2003
  - 1989
    - Brown, Douglas (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brown, J.N.B. "Bish" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chapman, J.A.D. (Adrian) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Footitt, Jim (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hart, J.A. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - List, Eric (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Ricks, G.W. (Gerry) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Robinson, Dave (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Soffe, Cindy and Mick (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Turner, Steve (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Wernery, Ullrich (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1990
    - Brown, Doug (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Brown, J.N.B. (Bish) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chapman, J.A.D. (Adrian) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Green, Simon and Roy (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Hart, J.A. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Pitt, Martin (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Richardson, R.A. (Bob) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ricks, G.W. (Gerry) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Robinson, Dave (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Soffe, Cindy and Mick (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Verhage, Martin (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous (1) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous (2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1991
    - Bannon, John (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Brown, J.N.B. (Bish) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chapman, J.A.D. (Adrian) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Green, Simon and Roy (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hart, J.A. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Morris, Rob P. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Richardson, R.A. (Bob) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Ricks, G.W. (Gerry) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Robinson, Dave (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Soffe, Cindy and Mick (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Tafforeau, Joachim (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Turner, Steve (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Verhage, Martin (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, forms (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, notes (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1992
    - Brown, J.N.B. "Bish" (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Cederoth, Christian and Johnsson, Pav (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chapman, J.A.D. (Adrian) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Feulner, Gary (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Flack, Eric (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Green, Simon and Roy (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - James, Steve (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Komi, Jarmo, and Santamaa, Markku (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Norton, John (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Numminen, Tapani, and Forster, Annike (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Philip, I. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Questen, Rob (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Richardson, R.A. (Bob) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Robinson, Dave (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1993
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Hirschfeld, Erik (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - James, Steve (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - McGill, Martin (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Paynter, Dave (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Read, Bob (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Richardson, R.A. (Bob) (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Tuomenoja, Tapio (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - 1994
    - Feulner, Gary (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hellyer, Peter (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hirschfeld, Erik (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hollingworth, Jenny (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - James, Steve (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Read, Robert (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Reaney, Len (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ruiters, Paul, and Guido Keyt (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Stawarczyk, Tadeusz, et. al. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous: telephoned sightings (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous: other (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 2002
    - January (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - February (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - March (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - April (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - May (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - June (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - July (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - August (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - September (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - October (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - November (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - December (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - 2003
    - January - February (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - March (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - April (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - May - November (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Group bird record forms: by individuals, 1990-2002
  - Aspinall, Simon
    - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1998 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1999 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 2000 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bourdin, Paul
    - 2000 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 2001 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 2002 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Brett, Phil
    - 1996 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1997 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1998 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1999 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Diskin, Dave
    - 2000 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - 2001 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - 2002 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Hellyer, Peter
    - 2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - James, Steve
    - 1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Reaney, Len
    - 1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Richardson, Colin
    - 1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1994 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1995 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 1997 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - 1998 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - 1999 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 2000 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Saunders, Clive
    - 1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1999 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 2000 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Twyman, Andrew
    - 1998 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 2000 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 2001 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Wood, Mike
    - 1990 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1991 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - 1992 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - 1993 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - 1994 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 1995 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1996 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1997 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1998 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Other records (analog), 1982-2006
  - Rare Birds in the UAE, 1982-2006
    - List, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Assessment, Summary charts, 1982-2005 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Forms, 1995-1997 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Forms, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Forms, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Forms, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Forms, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Forms, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Forms, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Forms, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Reprints of articles, 1988-2003
    - Uttley, J.D., et.al. "The Autumn Migration of Waders and other Waterbirds through the Northern United Arab Emirates." Sandgrouse, No. 10, pages 58-70., 1988 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Wardman, Oliver. "A Survey of Breeding, Wintering and Migratory Bird Populations in an Extensive Alluvial Acacia Plain in Arabia." Bachelors thesis for degree of BSc in Environmental Studies, University of Hertfordshire, undated, circa mid-1990s (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Clement, Peter and Helbig, Andreas. "Taxonomy and identification of chiffchaffs in the Western Palearctic." British Birds 91: 361-376, September 1998 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Potts, D.T. (Dan). "Ostrich distribution and exploitation in the Arabian peninsula." [inscribed by Potts to Simon Aspinall, March 2003]. Antiquity 75: 182-190, 2001, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Other records (digital), 1993-2019; 28.6 Megabytes in 49 files
  Preservica Public URL
  https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|488683c2-3f3a-47cd-8d57-36e35da08134/
  - Articles collected, 2009-2010; 13.0 Megabytes in 4 files, PDF
    https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|dbc40788-ec82-4aec-af78-451e12b752f0/
    - Campbell, Oscar and Tommy Pedersen. Birding in the United Arab Emirates, [October 2010] (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_001)
      Preservica Internal URL
      https://eu.preservica.com/explorer/explorer.html#prop:4&4592aea3-8652-425b-ac7d-11cc78ff7b02
      https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|4592aea3-8652-425b-ac7d-11cc78ff7b02/
    - Campbell, Oscar. "An apparent hybrid collared pratincole...and the oriental pratincole problem.", 2009 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_002)
      https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|1d7c369f-f5c0-4654-a64c-bce0df192d7d/
    - Kostolanyi, Andras, et. al. "Breeding ecology of Kentish Plover 'Charadrius alexandrina' in an extremely hot environment." Bird Study 2009, 56: 244-252. (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_003)
      https://eu.preservica.com/explorer/explorer.html#prop:4&0b9b2cab-625f-4a6c-8a18-a1c809d66dd2
      https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|0b9b2cab-625f-4a6c-8a18-a1c809d66dd2
    - Shorebirds of the Arabian Peninsula: Proceedings of the 10th Conservation Workshop for the Fauna of Arabia (Sharjah), February 2009 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_004)
      https://eu.preservica.com/explorer/explorer.html#prop:4&9422879d-f8fa-412e-ae08-cebef78f964d
      https://nyuad.access.preservica.com/archive/sdb%3Acollection|9422879d-f8fa-412e-ae08-cebef78f964d/
  - Bird reports: annual, 2011-2014; 4.0 Megabytes in 4 files, PDF
    - Bird of the United Arab Emirates: Annual Report, 2011 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_005)
    - Bird of the United Arab Emirates: Annual Report, 2012 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_006)
    - Birds of the United Arab Emirates: Annual Report, 2013 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_007)
    - Birds of the United Arab Emirates: Annual Report, 2014 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_008)
  - Bird reports: monthly, 2001-2002; 1.1 Megabytes in 6 files, RTF
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 6, September 2001 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_009)
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 8, November 2001 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_010)
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 9, December 2001 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_011)
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 10, January 2002 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_012)
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 11, February 2002 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_013)
    - Monthly Bird Report: No. 13, April 2002 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_014)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1993-2009; 0.6 Megabytes in 12 files, PDF
    - Meeting 1, 15 October 1993 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_015)
    - Meeting 3. Sweihan, 18 February 1994 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_016)
    - Meeting 4. Abu Dhabi, 27 May 1994 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_017)
    - Meeting 5. Ghantoot, 15 January 1995 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_018)
    - Meeting 6. Ghantoot, 29 November 1998 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_019)
    - Meeting 8. Ghantoot, 1 November 2001 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_020)
    - Meeting 9. Ghantoot, 3 January 2002 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_021)
    - Meeting 10. Ghantoot, 23 May 2002 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_022)
    - Meeting 11. Ghantoot, 6 March 2003 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_023)
    - Meeting 12. Jebel Ali, 19 November 2003 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_024)
    - Meeting 13. Ghantoot, 24 June 2004 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_025)
    - Meeting. Unnumbered. Abu Dhabi, 27 February 2009 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_026)
  - Other, 2009-2019; 8.2 Megabytes in 3 files, .xls, .docx, .eml
    - Rare Bird Assessments (Emirates Bird Records Group), 1998-2006 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_027)
    - Early Emirates Bird Report (to 1989): e-mail from Colin Richardson, 2009 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_028)
    - EBRC Report Form, January 2019 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_029)
  - Reports: 19, 1994-1997; 0.6 Megabytes in 10 files, PDF
    - Recently accepted UAE rarities, 1994-1996 (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_030)
    - Abu Dhabi Islands breeding bird survey (Richardson, Aspinall, Verhage) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_031)
    - An introduction to the birds of Jazirat Balghelam, Abu Dhabi (Hellyer, Aspinall) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_032)
    - Observations of territorial behaviour of Kentish Plover...at Khor Dubai (Frost, D.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_033)
    - Large white-headed gulls in the United Arab Emirates (Garner) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_034)
    - Emirates Bird Report 19: contents, (published 1997) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_035)
    - Mediterranean Gull .....at Ramtha Tip (James, S. and Norton, J.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_036)
    - A visit to Merawah Islands, 31 May / 1 June 1990 (Pitt, M.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_037)
    - The sub-species of house crow....in the UAE (Madge, S.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_038)
    - Systematic list of the birds reported in 1994 (Richardson, C.; Aspinall, S.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_039)
  - Reports: 20, 2000; 0.5 Megabytes in 9 files, PDF
    - Amur falcon...: the first record for the United Arab Emirates (Aspinall, S.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_040)
    - Common Noddy....: the first record for the United Arab Emirates (James, S.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_041)
    - The first record of Dunn's Lark....for the United Arab Emirates (Haag, H.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_042)
    - The first records of Intermediate Egret...in the United Arab Emirates (Aspinall, S.; Diskin, D.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_043)
    - The first record of Little Gull....in the United Arab Emirates (Dryden, M.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_044)
    - The first record of Lesser White-Fronted Goose...in the United Arab Emirates (Tunturi, M., et.al.) (Box Electronic records, E-records AD_MC_057_045)